<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Fishermen fishers of men A sermon preached at Mercers Chapell on Mid-Lent Sunday the 26. of March 1609. By Iohn Ravvlinson Doctour of Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Rawlinson, John, 1576-1630.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10496</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20772</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115678</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850896</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850896</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16132</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10496)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16132)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1253:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Fishermen fishers of men A sermon preached at Mercers Chapell on Mid-Lent Sunday the 26. of March 1609. By Iohn Ravvlinson Doctour of Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Rawlinson, John, 1576-1630.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Arnold Hatfield for Edward Blount and William Barret,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16132:1"/>
            <p>FISHERMEN Fiſhers of Men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED AT MERCERS Chapell on Mid-Lent <hi>Sunday the</hi> 26. <hi>of</hi> March 1609.</p>
            <p>By IOHN RAVVLINSON Doctour <hi>of Diuinitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Bernard. ad Henricum Senonenſem Archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcop.
Ep. <hi>42.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Non vos ergo foelicem, quia praeeſtis: ſed ſi non prodeſtis, infoelicem putate.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Arnold Hatfield</hi> for <hi>Edward Blount</hi> and <hi>William Barret.</hi> 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16132:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16132:2"/>
            <head>TO THE NOBLE AND Right virtuous Knight, Sir IOHN EGERTON, increaſe of <hi>true honour</hi> in this life, and fruition of <hi>true glory</hi> in the life to come.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>WORTHY SIR;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Muſt acknowledge my ſelfe to haue long run vpon the ſcore; ſo long, till <hi>Vſura ſuperat ſorte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> the <hi>intereſt</hi> of your loue exceeds the <hi>principall</hi> of my abilities: all which (if they be ought) you may therfore challenge as due debt, and arreſt them to bee continually at your ſeruice.</p>
            <p>Yet rather than I will ſhew my ſelfe a right bank-rupt, moſt vnkinde to him that hath beſt deſerued, and play off ſo kinde a Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour with <hi>Non ſum ſoluendo;</hi> I will grow to a faire and honest compoſition, and pay you (as I may) though it be but <hi>Vnciatim.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:16132:3"/>O that I could truly ſay with that ſeruant in the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 18 26.</note> Goſpel! <hi>Sir, haue patience with me, and I will pay you all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But<note n="(b)" place="margin">Bernar.</note> 
               <hi>exonerando me magis onero;</hi> The more J labour to requite, the more J ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige my ſelfe. For what doe J now but <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuram ſoluere,</hi> borrow both of your pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and protection to cleare the debt of your former fauours?</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ery likely that while J thus launch forth into the deep, and caſt my nette vpon the face of the waters, it will fare with me as with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fiſher-men, who among many fiſh meet with ſome <hi>Carps</hi> and if (by chance) they alight vpon a ſturdy <hi>Iack,</hi> there is great tug betwixt them, whether they ſhall catch the Jack, or the Jack them. But in this caſe J am of <hi>Seneca's</hi> reſolution;<note n="(d)" place="margin">Senec. epiſt. <hi>59.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cupio, ſi fieri poteſt, proitijs auribus quid ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, dicere; ſin minus, dicam &amp; iratis.</hi> And yet I hope without breach of charity too.
<pb facs="tcp:16132:3"/>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Gloſſ. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlin.</note> 
               <hi>Charitas ad ſaluandum violenta eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What allowance ſoeuer it ſhall find abroad, it humbly craues your fauourable acceptance at home: yea, it alſo preſumes, that becauſe it is your <hi>infant</hi> (for, but for you, it had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſeene light) it ſhall alſo be <hi>heire</hi> of your fauour; <hi>Nato filio nata portio.</hi> And that becauſe<note n="(f)" place="margin">Marſil. Ficin. in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</note> 
               <hi>Mercurius ante omnes ſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Phoebo ſemper eſt domeſticus;</hi> Your ſelf, who are learned <hi>Supraſortem ſupra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulgarem,</hi> will gladly patronise <hi>the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> of Diuines, which is the maine matter of this Sermon;</p>
            <p>A matter (if any other) very materiall &amp; neceſſary for theſe daies, becauſe as a ſpice of all other diſeaſes attends vpon the ague; and, <hi>Ad ignorationem elenchi reduci poſſunt omnes paralogiſmi:</hi> So the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and ſlender regard of Gods Miniſters is the matter and mother of all other enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb facs="tcp:16132:4"/>which ſo plentifully reigne in this irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular age of ours.</p>
            <p>Whatſoeuer it is elſe, it is the <hi>Votoria ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bula</hi> of my loue conſecrated to the <hi>Temple</hi> of your <hi>Honor,</hi> which ſhall daily be frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with my praiers vnto God; That as you, and your honourable good Lady are here <hi>Gemini in terra caro vna;</hi> ſo hereafter ye may be for euer <hi>Gemini in coelo, ſydus vnum:</hi> And that both the <hi>hopefull</hi> and <hi>hoped fruits</hi> of both your bodies may bee as truly heires of both your virtues, as your ſelf are of the manifold graces and bleſsings of your moſt honoured and honour-worthy <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> whoſe vnworthy, but moſt obſeruant <hi>ſeruant</hi> J am, and hartilie ioy to be.</p>
            <p>And, as <hi>Coelum quietem ſuam ſorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in motu;</hi> So in continuance of theſe my humble and hartie praiers vnto God for you, and yours, J ſhall euer reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt deuoted debtor, <hi>Iohn Ravvlinson.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:16132:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> SERMON PREACHED at Mercers Chapel on Mid-Lent Sunday the 26. <hi>of March.</hi> 1609.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>MATTH. <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 19.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Follow mee, and J will make you Fiſhers of men.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing elſewhere com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced the handling of this Scripture, which may fitly bee called <hi>Piſcatorum Scriptura: The Fiſhermans Scripture,</hi> and therefore (I truſt) not impertinent to <hi>this time,</hi> which may as fitly be termed <hi>Piſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16132:5"/>meſsis, The fiſhermans haruest;</hi> I will now (by Gods aſſiſtance, and your Chriſtian pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience) proceed to the vnfolding of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder.</p>
            <p>The words may be quartered into foure parts:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The <hi>calling</hi> of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Andrew</hi> (the 2 firſt Apoſtles) to the office of Apoſtleſhip: <hi>Follow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 The <hi>Caller,</hi> Chriſt himſelfe: <hi>Me.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 The <hi>Called, Peter</hi> and <hi>Andrew: You.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 The <hi>Function</hi> or <hi>Office</hi> whereunto they are called: <hi>Fiſhers of men.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1 The <hi>Calling</hi> was <hi>two-fold; Externall,</hi> and <hi>Internall.</hi> For to little purpoſe had been <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terior Oratio,</hi> The outward ſound &amp; miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Chriſt his voice, had it not beene ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with <hi>Interior Operatio,</hi> The inward worke and efficacie of his grace.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In the <hi>Caller</hi> are 2. things:</p>
            <p>The one is <hi>Affectus,</hi> his gratious and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing affection, calling them before they dr amt of his call.</p>
            <p>The other is <hi>Effectus,</hi> his powerfull and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16132:5"/>effectual working in them, in that he comes vnto them with a <hi>Fieri faciam:</hi> How vnapt &amp; vnable ſoeuer ye may deeme your ſelues, yet follow me, and it ſhall be <hi>your making.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 In the <hi>parties called</hi> I obſerue 3. things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Their <hi>Number:</hi> They were <hi>Two.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 Their <hi>Conſanguinitie:</hi> They were <hi>Brethren.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 Their <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition</hi> or <hi>Quality:</hi> They were <hi>poore, ignoble,</hi> and <hi>ignorant fiſhermen.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And vpon theſe three I ſpent my <hi>former diſcourſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 Now fourthly and laſtly, In the <hi>Office</hi> whereunto they are called, there are other three conſiderable points:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Their <hi>Dignity.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 Their <hi>Diligence.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 Their <hi>Diſcretion.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Dignity</hi> without <hi>Diligence,</hi> were but <hi>harts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe and idleneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diligence</hi> without <hi>Dignity,</hi> were but <hi>drudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and baſeneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Both</hi> without <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> were but <hi>ſimplicity and weakneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:16132:6"/>
But a <hi>full ſweet harmony of all three</hi> makes them apt and able to fulfill their miniſtery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All three</hi> inſinuated in this <hi>one Metaphor, Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catores hominum,</hi> Fiſhers of men.</p>
            <p>Firſt of the <hi>Metaphor;</hi> and then to the <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Sauiour in this ſo familiar and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticall a <hi>Metaphor</hi> deſcendeth to the vulgar &amp; ordinary phraſe of ſpeech, <hi>Quo factum po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterius prioris retinet nomen;</hi> Wherby the name of a thing formerly done is transferred to an after-buſineſſe: as, when a man hath been <hi>at his booke,</hi> if afterwards he betake himſelfe to ſome other worke, we are woont by way of Metaphor to bid him, <hi>Lege et hunc librum;</hi> Read mee alſo this booke.</p>
            <p>And wee read of King Dauid,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 78.71</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. that he was called <hi>from feeding of ſheepe,</hi> to bee <hi>a ſhepheard of men.</hi> And heere we ſee <hi>Peter and Andrew</hi> called <hi>from catching of fiſh,</hi> to be <hi>fiſhers of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obſerue, and ye ſhall finde, that it is the vſuall practiſe of our Sauiour to ſpeake of ſpirituall things as if they were corporall,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16132:6"/>
               <hi>Vt ad excellentiam diuinarum rerum per corporalia homines attollat</hi> (ſaith<note n="b" place="margin">Hil. l. <hi>6.</hi> de Triuit.</note> 
               <hi>S. Hilary</hi>) that ſo he may raiſe our groueling and earth-creeping affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to an higher leuill, and weane them from corporall and temporall things to the conſideration of things ſpirituall.</p>
            <p>No ſooner had the woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him his <hi>Q.</hi> by talking with him of <hi>mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial water,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Io. 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>Io.</hi> 4. but he preſently takes occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to tell her of <hi>his word,</hi> that it is the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> able to reuiue a ſoule dead in ſinne.</p>
            <p>And<note n="d" place="margin">Io. 6.27.</note> 
               <hi>Io.</hi> 6. when the <hi>Capernaits</hi> follow him for <hi>loaues and fiſhes,</hi> he willes them, <hi>not to labour for the meat that periſheth, but for the meat that endureth to euerlasting life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſonant hereunto is that ancient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome (which albeit this refined age of ours haue branded with a note of Superſtition, yet hath nothing (for ought I know) but laudable antiquity to diſcommend it) when a <hi>light</hi> is ſet before vs in the darke, as it were with a <hi>Surſum corda,</hi> to erect the harts and mindes of ſuch as are preſent, with, <hi>God ſend
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16132:7"/>vs the light in heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſurely, if <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that which may be knowen of God the Creator, doth ſhine in theſe his inferiour creatures: and if <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> theſe things which may beſeene, doe lead &amp; hand vs on to thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> inuiſible things of God,<note n="e" place="margin">Ro. 1.19. &amp; 20.</note> 
               <hi>Ro.</hi> 1. No queſtion but this rearing and mounting of our thoughts from earth to heauen, is a thing not lawfull onely, but withall ſo expedient, that neglect it we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, but we muſt be iniurious to <hi>God,</hi> his <hi>creatures,</hi> and <hi>our ſelues. God himſelfe</hi> is diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, if his <hi>creatures</hi> be neglected; his <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> are neglected, if we receiue no inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from them: And what inſtruction can we receiue from <hi>them,</hi> if wee onely plod and pore vpon this <hi>great booke of nature,</hi> and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer tranſlate it into the <hi>booke of grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore doth our Sauiour in this place teach vs to alienate our thoughts from earth to heauen, from things temporall to things ſpirituall, by conuerting the paines and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of theſe ſilly fiſhermen from the <hi>catching of fiſh,</hi> to the <hi>catching of men.</hi> They muſt ſtill
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16132:7"/>fiſh, but it muſt be <hi>Quid pro quo;</hi> One for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother: <hi>Men</hi> for <hi>Fiſh.</hi> Not changing their <hi>perſon,</hi> but their <hi>office:</hi> not their <hi>industrie,</hi> but their <hi>profeſsion:</hi> not their <hi>appellation,</hi> but onely their <hi>vocation:</hi>
            </p>
            <q>I will make you fiſhers of men.</q>
            <p>Not a <hi>Metaphor</hi> thorowout the whole vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume of Gods booke, that more willingly dilates and ſpreads it ſelfe into an <hi>allegory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 For firſt, <hi>Piſcatores, Apostoli:</hi> The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and their Succeſſours the faithfull Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt, are called <hi>Fiſhers,</hi> in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the <hi>spirituall fiſh,</hi> which they catch: in Greek<note n="f" place="margin">Eraſm. in Matth. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, either <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of the ſea of this world wherein they fiſh: or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of catching, becauſe they labour to catch men, and with the <hi>draw-net</hi> of <hi>Gods word</hi> to draw them<note n="g" place="margin">Ro. 10.17</note> by the eares, <hi>A ſaeculo,</hi> from the ſea of this world, u <hi>Ad ſaecula ſaeculorum,</hi> to the ſhore of a better life, euen <hi>the land of the liuing,</hi> that (as<note n="h" place="margin">Chryſoſt. Hom. <hi>7.</hi> oper. imperf.</note> 
               <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>hom.</hi> 7. <hi>oper. imperf.</hi>) <hi>being thither tranſlated, there they may liue as members incorporate into the body of Chriſt:</hi> &amp; that they may be<note n="i" place="margin">Bern. Ser. 1. in die S. Andr.</note> 
               <hi>Digni qui in mensâ
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16132:8"/>Dominicâ ponantur:</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Bernard</hi>) fit to be ſerued in at the Lords Table.</p>
            <p>Theſe be the <hi>fiſhers</hi> mentioned<note n="k" place="margin">Ier. 16.16</note> 
               <hi>Ier.</hi> 16. <hi>Mittam piſcatores multos, &amp; piſcabuntur eos,</hi> ſaith God by his Prophet; I wil ſend among them many fiſhers, and they ſhall fiſh them. And theſe the <hi>fiſhers</hi> ſpoken of<note n="l" place="margin">Ezech. 47.10.</note> 
               <hi>Ezech.</hi> 47. where the Prophet ſaw in a viſion their <hi>nets ſtretched out from Engaddi to Engallim,</hi> from the one end of the <hi>Mare mortuum</hi> of this world, to the other end of the ſame.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Piſces, homines.</hi> The fiſhes are here ſpecified to be men; Land-fiſh, not Sea-fiſh. It is fabled by<note n="m" place="margin">Ouid. Metam. l. <hi>3.</hi> f. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> the Poet, that <hi>Bacchus</hi> began his Empire with the <hi>tranſmutation of mariners into fiſhes:</hi> So doth Chriſt the <hi>true Bacchus, Bis genitus</hi> (<hi>God</hi> of the ſubſtance of his father begotten before the world, and <hi>man</hi> of the ſubſtance of his mother borne in the world) begin <hi>his kingdome,</hi> euen <hi>the kingdome of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,</hi> with the <hi>metamorphiſing</hi> of <hi>men</hi> into <hi>fiſhes,</hi> yet doth he not either <hi>tranſubſtantiate</hi> them into <hi>fiſhes,</hi> like thoſe <hi>mariners:</hi> or, <hi>ingulfe</hi> them into the <hi>bellie of a fiſh,</hi> like <hi>Ionas:</hi> or, make
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16132:8"/>them <hi>fiſh</hi> the one halfe, <hi>fleſh</hi> the other, like <hi>Myrmaides;</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Horat. Art. poet.</note> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t turpiter atrum</l>
               <l>Deſinat in piſcem Mulier formoſa ſupernè</l>
            </q>
            <p>But herein wil he haue them to ſymbolize with fiſhes, that as <hi>fiſhes</hi> are caught <hi>lineis textis,</hi> with a net of twiſted lines: ſo muſt they be caught <hi>lineis ex Scripturâ contextis,</hi> with the net of Gods word made of lines taken out of the text of Scripture.</p>
            <p>True is that of theſe <hi>ſpirituall fiſhes,</hi> which <hi>Philoxenus</hi> in<note n="o" place="margin">Plutarch. de aud. poet.</note> 
               <hi>Plutarch</hi> (<hi>Epicure</hi> as hee was!) ſpake in a <hi>ſenſuall ſenſe; Ex piſcibus qui non ſunt piſces, ſuauiſsimi:</hi> Theſe which indeed are no fiſh, but men, are the beſt, the ſweeteſt, the moſt pretious kinde of fiſh.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſemblances</hi> wherein <hi>men</hi> accord with <hi>fiſh</hi> are diuerſe. I will name but ſome few of many.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Our Sauiour<note n="p" place="margin">Luc. 9.16.</note> 
               <hi>Luc.</hi> 9. ſo <hi>miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly bleſſed</hi> the two fiſhes wherewith hee fed the many, that by virtue of that <hi>bleſsing</hi> they were exceedinglie multiplied. So did God at the beginning in that <hi>miracle of mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:16132:9"/>(the creation of the world) ſo bleſſ <hi>Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Eue</hi> (the 2. firſt fiſhes (with a <hi>Creſcite &amp; mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicamini,</hi> increaſe and multiply<note n="q" place="margin">Gen. 1.28</note> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. that ere long the <hi>bleſsing of Iacob</hi> fell vpon them<note n="r" place="margin">Gen. 48.16.</note> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 48. they <hi>grew as fiſh into a multitude,</hi> euen into a <hi>world</hi> of men and women.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Againe: As fiſh muſt: <hi>ſwimme</hi> thrice; namely, in <hi>water,</hi> in <hi>vineger,</hi> and in <hi>wine:</hi> So muſt euery <hi>Chriſtian</hi> man: Firſt, in the <hi>water of Baptiſme,</hi> wherby we are <hi>Nati &amp; Initiati,</hi> born &amp; initiated into the Church of Chriſt, as we are taught by<note n="ſ" place="margin">Tertull. l. de Baptiſm.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian lib. de Baptiſm.</hi> Then in the <hi>Vineger of ſharpe perſecution,</hi> whereof our Sauiour dranke deepe at his paſsion,<note n="t" place="margin">Matt. 27.48.</note> 
               <hi>Matt.</hi> 27. And laſtly, in the <hi>wine of the Euchariſt,</hi> which is<note n="u" place="margin">Zach. 9. vlt.</note> 
               <hi>Vinum germinans virgines,</hi> the wine of virginity, <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p n="3">3 As fiſhes taken out of <hi>their element,</hi> by and by <hi>die:</hi> ſo<note n="*" place="margin">Chryſoſt. hom. <hi>1.</hi> ad pop. Antioch Tertull. l. de Baptiſm.</note> without the pure <hi>element of God word,</hi> (the <hi>water of life</hi>) to refrigerate and coole the languiſhing ſoule, we die, and are extinct, and giue vp the (holie) Ghoſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4 As <hi>brine</hi> keepes fiſh from <hi>putrefaction:</hi> ſo the <hi>brackiſh,</hi> and <hi>briniſh waters of repentance,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16132:9"/>(our paenitent teares)</hi> are <hi>Animae pro ſale,</hi> to the ſoule in ſtead of ſalt, to keepe it from the <hi>corruption and tainture of ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 As thoſe fiſhes onely were reputed <hi>cleane, Qui pinnulas &amp; ſquamas habent,</hi> which haue finnes &amp; ſcales,<note n="x" place="margin">Deut. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Deut.</hi> 14. So are thoſe men only <hi>cleane</hi> in the ſight of God, <hi>Qui ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas &amp; loricam habent patientiae, &amp; pinnulas hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laritatis</hi> (ſaith<note n="y" place="margin">Bernard. Serm. <hi>1.</hi> in die S. Andr.</note> 
               <hi>S. Bernard</hi>) who haue the ſcales and coat-armour of patience, and the finnes of ioy and cheerfulneſſe to ſpring vp to God-ward.</p>
            <p n="6">6 As there are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, fiſhes that eat vp fiſhes; the greater the leſſe,</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Oppian. l. <hi>2.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <p>So there are alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; Men that eat vp men: an vnchriſtian kind of <hi>Canibals, eating vp Gods people as a man would eat bread,</hi> as it is<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 14.8.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14. And it is the complaint of the Prophet<note n="b" place="margin">Abac. 1.14.</note> 
               <hi>Abacuc, c.</hi> 1. <hi>Facis homines quaſipiſces maris:</hi> Thou (O God) makeſt men as the fiſhes of the ſea, feeding and praying one vpon another.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:16132:10"/>
7 As fiſhes <hi>Tunduntur fluctibus, &amp; non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiunt</hi> (ſaith<note n="c" place="margin">Haymo.</note> 
               <hi>Haymo</hi>) are ſouſed with the ſalt and bitter waues, and yet ſinke not: ſo are thegodly billow-beaten with perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and yet faint not. For this (ſaith<note n="d" place="margin">Hilar. l. <hi>7.</hi> de Trinit.</note> S. <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary l.</hi> 7. <hi>de Trinit.</hi>), is the prerogatiue of Gods Church: <hi>While it is perſecuted, it flouriſheth: while oppreſſed, it increaſeth: while contemned, it proſpereth: while aſſaulted, it vanquiſheth: while tried, it vnderſtandeth: nay, though almost conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſtill it withſtandeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8, And laſtly, as fiſhes when they are wounded, haue recourſe to the <hi>Tench,</hi> the <hi>Phyſitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of fiſhes,</hi> whom if they do but touch, they are healed: So muſt wee when wee are <hi>wounded with ſin,</hi> repaire to our Sauior Chriſt the <hi>true tench,</hi> the <hi>Phyſitian of Kings,</hi> and <hi>King of Phyſitians,</hi> whom if we doe but touch <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu fidei,</hi> with the touch of true faith, we ſhall bee <hi>whole:</hi> as the <hi>woman with the bloody iſſue,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Luc. 8.44</note> 
               <hi>Luc.</hi> 8. toucht but the hem of his garment onely, and ſhe was preſently <hi>whole as a fiſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is therefore well and wittily obſerued by the ancient (as is noted by<note n="f" place="margin">Auguſt. De ciuit. l. <hi>18.</hi> c. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>S. Auſtin, de
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16132:10"/>Ciuit. l.</hi> 18. <hi>c.</hi> 23. and by<note n="g" place="margin">Tertull. li. de Baptiſm.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian lib. de Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm.</hi>) that the <hi>initiall letters</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: (Ieſus Chriſt the Son of God our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or) make vp the <hi>Greeke word</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth <hi>a fiſh.</hi> And ye ſhall finde,<note n="h" place="margin">Iohn 19.34.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> 19. that at his paſsion hee was <hi>opened in the ſide,</hi> like a <hi>fiſh.</hi> And the <hi>Authour of the Sermons de Sanctis,</hi> vnder <hi>S. Auſtins</hi> name, compares him to <hi>Tobits fiſh, Cuius iecore per paſsionem aſſato fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatus eſt Diabolus:</hi> Whoſe liuer being broiled at his paſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fiery coales of his loue, did ſcare and driue away the vnclean ſpirit.</p>
            <p>In theſe, and the like reſpects, are men ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſemblable vnto fiſhes. And yet, this <hi>diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> I find between them, that wheras whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fiſhes, are taken, its death to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; when men are taken, its life to them. For fiſhes are taken that they may be deuoured by the <hi>iawes of men;</hi> but men are taken that they may bee <hi>deliuered</hi> from the <hi>iawes of hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Mare, ſaeculum.</hi> The Sea, wherein they fiſh, is the world: <hi>Mare magnum &amp; ſpacioſum,</hi> a wide and wilde Sea, as <hi>Dauid</hi> calls it<note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 104.25.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104. Or (as<note n="k" place="margin">Apoc. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>S. Iohn</hi> termes it, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 4. <hi>Mare
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16132:11"/>vitreum:</hi> A Sea of glaſſe; a <hi>Sea,</hi> for <hi>tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuouſneſſe;</hi> and a Sea of <hi>glaſſe,</hi> for <hi>brittleneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the time of <hi>Noah, that preacher of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> then was it true without a metaphor, that all the World was nothing elſe but a <hi>Sea,</hi> or <hi>deluge,</hi> when the waters had ouerſpred the whole ſurface of the earth:<note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 7.18.</note> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Ouid. Met. l. <hi>1.</hi> f. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Omnia Pontus erant, deerant quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> litora Ponto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was then a <hi>materiall,</hi> now a <hi>myſticall ſea,</hi> wherein are many <hi>conflicts</hi> of <hi>croſſe-windes,</hi> and <hi>waters; tide</hi> againſt <hi>wind,</hi> and <hi>wind</hi> againſt <hi>tide,</hi> and <hi>both</hi> againſt <hi>fiſhers, the Preachers of righteouſneſse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Sea,</hi> wherein the <hi>Diuell,</hi> that <hi>huge Leuia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> of whom it is ſaid<note n="n" place="margin">Iob 41.7.</note> 
               <hi>Iob</hi> 41. that <hi>Squama ſquamae coniungitur, &amp; ſpiraculum non eſt in eis;</hi> His ſcales are ſo cloſe compacted together, that no winde can come between them, not onely <hi>plaies and takes his paſtime,</hi> (<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 104.26.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.) but his <hi>paſtime</hi> is, <hi>to ſpoile the riuer, and to ſucke vp Iordan into his mouth,</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Iob 40.18</note> 
               <hi>Iob</hi> 40. And a <hi>Sea,</hi> wherein (as<note n="q" place="margin">Chryſoſt. Hom. <hi>7.</hi> oper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imperf.</note> 
               <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> notes) <hi>Homines non ambulant, ſed feruntur, quia Diabolus cum dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatione compellit eos in mala:</hi> Men walke not,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16132:11"/>but are carried with the ſtreame, while the Diuel carries the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> headlong into ſin: whence it is, that many make <hi>ſhipwracke of faith and a good conſcience:</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">1. Tim. 1.19.</note> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. and then what mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell if they be <hi>drowned in perdition and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.9</note> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. But moſt of vs (beat the waues neuer ſo little) Lord! how ſoone are we <hi>ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke?</hi> Scarſe able with the <hi>Diſciples,</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Matt. 8.25.</note> 
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 8. when their ſhip was endangered, to ſob out ſo much as a ſhort diſiointed eiaculation; <hi>Lord, ſaue vs, we periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Cymba, vocatio.</hi> The fiſher-boat is the profeſsion or calling of the Miniſter, which howſoeuer heere in this world it be like the ſhip <hi>Argos; Militans inter fluctus,</hi> daily and hourely expoſed to the ſore and bitter tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts of perſecution, hatred, exile, death it ſelfe: yet heereafter it ſhall be like the ſame ſhip, <hi>Inter ſydera triumphans,</hi> as the ſtars in the firmament, ſhining for euer and euer.<note n="u" place="margin">Dan. 12.3</note> 
               <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Rete, verbum.</hi> The Net is not any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall Net, like that in<note n="*" place="margin">Suidas,</note> 
               <hi>Suidas,</hi> which one caſt ouer another while they were in ſingle
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16132:12"/>combate together, &amp; when he had enſnared him in his net, ſlew him. Nor ſuch a phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical, imaginary Net, as is <hi>Purgatory;</hi> which<note n="x" place="margin">Szeg. ſpec. Pont. Rom.</note> 
               <hi>Szegedin</hi> cals <hi>Ampliſsimum rete ad capiendas ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas;</hi> A moſt ſpacious Net to intangle ſouls: Nor ſuch a <hi>bloody ſpiritual Net,</hi> as<note n="y" place="margin">Mich. 7.2.</note> the Prophet <hi>Micah</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>All lie in wait for blood: euery man hunteth his brother with a net.</hi> But it is <hi>Sagena,</hi> that <hi>ſweepe-net,</hi> which our Sauiour brought downe from heauen, euen the <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Goſpel</hi> of Ieſus Chriſt, catching whole nations at a draught: that <hi>Net,</hi> wherin men, who are plunged in the darkeſome holes of ignorance, &amp; muddy cares of this world, are drag'd and drawen out to the light of truth, and loue of ſupernall things.</p>
            <p>Or (as<note n="z" place="margin">Ber. Ser. <hi>1.</hi> in die S. Andr.</note> 
               <hi>S. Bernard</hi> hath it) <hi>Naſſa eccleſia eſt:</hi> The <hi>weele</hi> is the Church of God: <hi>Quae li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cèt homines certis legibus &amp; ceremonijs retineat;</hi> which though it keepe men vnder certaine lawes and ceremonies, yet it ſo keeps them vnder, that it alſo ſecures them from being ſwallowed vp of other mighty ſea-mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſters, ſuch as are heretikes and ſchiſmatikes.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:16132:12"/>
6 <hi>Nauclerus, Clerus.</hi> The <hi>guide or Pilot</hi> of this fiſh-boate is the <hi>Clergie,</hi> or rather <hi>Chriſt himſelfe,</hi> the high-Prieſt of our high-calling, who ſits at the ſterne, and guides both the boat and boat-men. Hee is the <hi>head-fiſher,</hi> wee but <hi>vnder-fiſhers.</hi> All our <hi>ſufficiency is of him,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">2. Cor. 2.6</note> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. And without him wee may <hi>labour all night,</hi> and yet catch not ſo much as an eie of fiſh,<note n="b" place="margin">Luc. 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>Luc.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>Wee muſt not then <hi>ſacrifice to our owne net,</hi> or <hi>burne incenſe to our owne yarne,</hi> as they did<note n="c" place="margin">Abac. 1.16</note> 
               <hi>Abac.</hi> 1. as if we could haue any great catch of our ſelues, but wee muſt ſay with <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Luc. 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>Luc.</hi> 5. <hi>In verbo tuo laxabo rete:</hi> At thy word (ô Chriſt) I will let downe the net, and then ſhall wee catch fiſh more than our net can hold.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Laſtly, <hi>Collectores, Angeli.</hi> The net re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues fiſh of both ſorts, bad aſwel as good,<note n="e" place="margin">Matth. 13.47.</note> 
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. All is fiſh that comes to net: but yet more comes to the net, than goes to the market. For the <hi>Angels</hi> at the conſummati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and end of the World ſhall gather the good <hi>In vaſa coeleſtium manſionum,</hi> into the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16132:13"/>of heauenly manſions: <hi>Malos autem tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendos &amp; exiccandos gehennae flamma ſuſcipiet:</hi> But the bad (ſaith<note n="f" place="margin">Raban. in Matth. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rabanus</hi>) ſhall for euer be fried and dried in that neuer-ending flame of hell fire.</p>
            <p>And ſo I come from the <hi>Metaphor,</hi> to the <hi>Matter</hi> it ſelfe, including (as I told you) three remarkable points:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The firſt, is the <hi>height and dignity</hi> of the Apoſtles calling. They are <hi>fiſhers,</hi> and that of <hi>men,</hi> the nobleſt kinde of fiſh.</item>
               <item>2 Their <hi>paines and diligence.</hi> They are <hi>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhers,</hi> and that of <hi>men,</hi> the wildeſt kinde of fiſh.</item>
               <item>3 Their <hi>wiſedome and diſcretion.</hi> They are <hi>fiſhers,</hi> and that of <hi>men,</hi> the wilieſt kinde of fiſh, too-cunning to bee caught, vnleſſe the bait be well tempered.</item>
            </list>
            <p>I ſhall now ſpeak only of the firſt, which is their <hi>Dignity.</hi> True it is, that (as<note n="g" place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>S. Bernard</hi> notes) <hi>Nemo repentè fit ſummus:</hi> Its more than a ſtep from the loweſt to the higheſt. And <hi>Aſcendendo, non volando, apprehenditur ſummitas ſcalae;</hi> Its climing, not flying, that brings a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16132:13"/>man to the top of the ladder. And yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold heere a ſtrange and ſudden alteration; ω ſtept into the place of α; The <hi>laſt</hi> became <hi>firſt,</hi> and the <hi>loweſt, higheſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Baſe, beggarly, and deſpicable was their former trade of fiſhing: But heere our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our comes, as<note n="h" place="margin">Luc. 14.10</note> 
               <hi>Luc.</hi> 14. with <hi>Amice, aſcende ſuperiù:</hi> Friend, ſit vp higher; and now muſt they haue worſhip in the preſence of all that are with them. For high and honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is the vocation whereunto they are now called. They are <hi>Piſcatores hominum:</hi> Fiſhers of men.</p>
            <p>Which title heere giuen them by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt, declares the <hi>manifold dignity</hi> of his Miniſters:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>Quoad Authorem.</hi> In regard of the <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor;</hi> That their profeſsion is not <hi>Inuentum humanum,</hi> an humane inuention; but <hi>Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum diuinum,</hi> a diuine inſtitution; heere licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vnder the broad ſeale of heauen, and authoriſed with a <hi>Fieri faciam:</hi> ſuch yee ſhall be, becauſe ſuch <hi>I will make you</hi> to be.</p>
            <p>Needs muſt that be a thrice-noble office,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16132:14"/>which is ennobled by the three ſtates-royal of heauen (the bleſſed Trinity) and enacted in that higheſt Court of Parliament.</p>
            <p>For the firſt Preacher that euer was, was <hi>God the Father,</hi> when he preached that ſweet and comfortable Goſpell in Paradiſe, <hi>Semen mulieris,</hi> The ſeed of the woman ſhall break the head of the Serpent,<note n="i" place="margin">Gen. 3.15</note> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>And our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt,</hi> did not only giue to his Church <hi>ſome to be Apoſtle, ſome Prophets, ſome Euangeliſts, ſome Paſtors and Doctors,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Eph. 4.11</note> 
               <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. but was himſelfe alſo <hi>anointed with the ſpirit of the Lord, and appointed to preach the Gospell to the poore,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Eſa. 61.1.</note> 
               <hi>Eſa.</hi> 61. And becauſe as hee ſent his Apoſtles, ſo was himſelfe alſo ſent of the father, therefore doth hee participate with his Apoſtles in name, and is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Apoſtle and high-Prieſt of our profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Heb. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>And<note n="n" place="margin">2. Pet. 1. vlt.</note> 
               <hi>S. Peter</hi> tels vs, <hi>ep.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1. that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men of God ſpake as they were mooued by <hi>the holy Ghoſt.</hi> And not only ſo, but that they alſo deriued their authority from the ſame ſpirit. Looke well to the flock, wherof
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16132:14"/>
               <hi>the holy Ghoſt hath made you ouer-ſeers,</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Act. 20.28.</note> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Quoad Authoritatem.</hi> In regard of their <hi>authority,</hi> which is not <hi>Imperium in belluas,</hi> but in <hi>homines,</hi> the rule and guidance not of beaſts, but men. For therfore are they <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, called of God, that they may bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, comforters of men: being <hi>Alae columbae dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentatae,</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> cals them,<note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 67.14.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 67. the <hi>ſiluer wings</hi> of that innocent Doue the holy Ghoſt, the true Comforter. And they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Apoſtles (by interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) <hi>men ſent from God,</hi> that men may be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, their <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> or <hi>letters of commendation</hi> ſent backe againe to God:<note n="q" place="margin">2. Cor. 3.2</note> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>None might come to <hi>Penelope,</hi> but by her maides: none to <hi>Pharao,</hi> but by <hi>Ioſeph:</hi> No more can any come to <hi>God,</hi> but by his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters. For <hi>ſaluation comes by faith: faith by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: hearing by the word of God: &amp; heare the word we cannot without a Preacher:</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 10.14.</note> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>No <hi>title</hi> of ſoueraignty that the earth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foords, but the Scripture affoords it them. For whereas the <hi>name of men</hi> is alike commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated vnto all, euen vnto the wicked aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16132:15"/>as the godly; (<hi>Cauete ab hominibus,</hi> Beware of men, ſaith our Sauiour,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Matt. 10.17.</note> 
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. that is, of cruell and wicked men) the Miniſters of Chriſt are by ſpeciall prerogatiue called, <hi>Homines Dei:</hi> The men of God:<note n="t" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.11.</note> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>watch-tower of Gods Church,</hi> they are not only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſeers,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ouer-ſeers,</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Act. 20.28.</note> 
               <hi>Acts</hi> 20.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>family of Gods Church,</hi> they are not only <hi>Patres,</hi> Fathers,<note n="*" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.23.</note> begetting vs with the immortall <hi>ſeed of the word,</hi> but they are alſo <hi>Nutritij,</hi> nurſing fathers,<note n="x" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.2.</note> feeding vs with the <hi>ſincere milke of the word:</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>kingdom of Gods Church,</hi> they are not only, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Sirs,</hi> or <hi>Lords:</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Act. 16.30.</note> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 16. but they are alſo <hi>Principes,</hi> Gods <hi>Vicars,</hi> or <hi>Vice-roys,</hi> heere on earth. For of them doth <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> expound thoſe words,<note n="z" place="margin">Pſal. 44.18.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44. <hi>Conſtitues eos Principes ſuper omnem terram:</hi> Thou ſhalt ſet them as <hi>Princes</hi> in all lands. Princes, for their <hi>nobility,</hi> becauſe they are begotten and born of God. Princes, for their <hi>riches,</hi> becauſe they are inriched with all ſpirituall graces: and Princes, for their <hi>power,</hi> becauſe they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16132:15"/>haue the power of the keies of the kingdom of heauen.</p>
            <p>Nay, as if the <hi>earth</hi> had not <hi>titles</hi> high e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, the Scripture goeth as high as <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> for titles for them. For they are <hi>Coeli,</hi> thoſe heauens that declare the glory of God<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 19.1.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. God dwelleth in them, ſpeaketh in them, ſhineth in them, as in the heauens.</p>
            <p>They are <hi>Angeli Domini exercituum,</hi> Angels of the Lord of Hoſts,<note n="b" place="margin">Malach. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>Malach.</hi> 2. So called (ſaith<note n="c" place="margin">Greg. in Matth.</note> 
               <hi>S. Gregory</hi>) <hi>Vt dignitatem ſeruent in nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, quam explent in operatione:</hi> that they might retaine that dignity in name, whereunto by office they are entitled.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, They are <hi>Dij terrae,</hi> thoſe Gods of the earth (as<note n="d" place="margin">Ferus in feſt. S. Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholom.</note> 
               <hi>Ferus</hi> expounds the place) ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 46. vlt.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46. <hi>Dij terrae vehementèr eleuati ſunt:</hi> The Gods of the Earth (to wit, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles) are highly exalted by their mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, but aboue all, by that greateſt miracle, the conuerſion of the world.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>Quoad Materiam.</hi> In regard of the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> they intreat of; <hi>The oracles of God:</hi> the <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of faith:</hi> the <hi>glad tidings of ſaluation:</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:16132:16"/>The <hi>Goſpell of the kingdome: The word of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation:</hi> the <hi>word of grace:</hi> and (in a word) <hi>The word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is that <hi>Magna charta,</hi> Gods <hi>great char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> by which we hold our ſaluation: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Magna charta,</hi> a moſt <hi>ſure card,</hi> to ſaile by, thorow the raging ſurges of this troubleſome world.</p>
            <p>This that <hi>Fauus mellis,</hi> that hony-combe, which when <hi>Ionatha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> had taſted, his eies were illightned,<note n="f" place="margin">1. Sam. 14.27.</note> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p>This that <hi>Panis ſubcinericius ex hordeo,</hi> that barley loafe,<note n="g" place="margin">Iud. 7.13.</note> 
               <hi>Iud.</hi> 7. which in the time of <hi>Gedeon,</hi> went rolling about, &amp; deſcended to the camps of the <hi>Midianites,</hi> &amp; when it came to any Tabernacle of theirs, did ſtrike it, and ouerturne it, and euen it with the ground.</p>
            <p>This that <hi>Manna,</hi> that <hi>cibus bidui,</hi> that two daies food,<note n="h" place="margin">Exod. 16.29.</note> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. feeding our ſouls both for this life, and that which is to come.</p>
            <p>And this that <hi>The ſaurus pretioſus,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">2 Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7</note> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. though brought vnto vs in earthen veſſels, yet a <hi>treaſure,</hi> yea and that a moſt pretious reaſure.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:16132:16"/>
4 <hi>Quoad depoſitum.</hi> In regard of the <hi>charge</hi> wherewith they are intruſted: That <hi>charge,</hi> the <hi>Church of Chriſt:</hi> the <hi>flocke of Chriſt:</hi> the <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt: the ſpouſe of Chriſt:</hi> the <hi>purchaſe, and price of the blood of Chriſt:</hi> the <hi>mother, brethren, and ſiſters of Chriſt:</hi> A <hi>choſen vine: an holy nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: a royall Prieſthood.</hi> The <hi>city of God:</hi> the <hi>Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Citizens with the Saints:</hi> the <hi>heires of God,</hi> and <hi>fellow-heires with Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Quoad Finem.</hi> In regard of the <hi>fruit and end of</hi> their calling, which is <hi>Lucrum animarum,</hi> the <hi>conuerting and gaining of</hi> ſoules vnto God, <hi>Quaeſtus multo vberrimus:</hi> the <hi>greateſt game</hi> in the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Piſcantur, vt homines adipiſcantur.</hi> Their fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing is, or ought to be, only <hi>for men.</hi> I ſay, the <hi>ſcope and end</hi> of their preaching muſt be, not <hi>Honorum Piſcatura,</hi> a fiſhing for honour, which<note n="k" place="margin">Cicer. in Academ. vid. Muret. var lect. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tully</hi> in his Academicks cals, <hi>Honores adhamare,</hi> hooking for honours: Nor <hi>Captura pecuniarum,</hi> the taking or money (which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is the <hi>Man</hi> that moſt men fiſh for) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Money, money is the man,</hi> ſaith<note n="l" place="margin">Pindar.</note> 
               <hi>Pindarus:</hi> and moſt men come with their
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16132:17"/>
               <hi>purſe-nets</hi> to fiſh for this man: But their <hi>end</hi> muſt be only <hi>Captura hominum,</hi> the taking of men; and their <hi>ſincerity</hi> ſuch as <hi>S. Pauls,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">2. Cor. 12 14.</note> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>I ſeeke not yours, but you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If then <hi>Diuinity</hi> haue ſo noble an end, as is the ſauing of man the nobleſt creature, well may it be called <hi>Nobiliſsima ſcientiarum,</hi> the nobleſt ſcience, and as well doth it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue to be <hi>Scientia nobiliſsimorum,</hi> the ſcience of the nobleſt.</p>
            <p>Compare it with other ſciences, and they are to it but as <hi>the roddes</hi> of the <hi>Magicians</hi> to the <hi>rod of Aaron;</hi> The rod of <hi>Aaron</hi> deuoures them all:<note n="n" place="margin">Exod. 7.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 7. The moſt they can doe, is but onely with <hi>Moſes</hi> to bring the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> out of the darkſome <hi>Aegypt</hi> of ignorance. None but this our <hi>Ioſuah,</hi> our <hi>ſauing knowledge of Diuinity,</hi> can bring them into the <hi>land of promiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Strange is the <hi>riddle,</hi> wherwith the fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in<note n="o" place="margin">Herodot. in vit. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</note> 
               <hi>Herodotus</hi> poſed <hi>Homer; Quae cepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, reliquimus: quae non cepimus, nobiſcum por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamus:</hi> That which we tooke, we left behind
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16132:17"/>vs: that which we tooke not, we carry with vs. More ſtrange, and yet quite contrarie, is the <hi>riddle of our ſaluation,</hi> propounded vnto vs by <hi>S. Paul,</hi> a <hi>ſpirituall fiſherman,</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">1. Cor. 1.21.</note> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>Per ſtultitiam praedicationis ſalus credentium:</hi> The ſauing of beleeuers by the fooliſhneſſe of Preaching;</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Si caperit, vitam (mirabile) liber adibis:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non captus, rigidae ius patiere necis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If thou be caught, thou liueſt: if loſt, thou dieſt.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>But, that which yet more commends the <hi>fruit and end</hi> of their calling, is the <hi>Latitude and extent</hi> thereof. They are <hi>Piſcatores hominum, Fiſhers,</hi> not of <hi>ſome,</hi> but <hi>indifferently of all men.</hi> For howſoeuer <hi>mans Law,</hi> be but <hi>Tela araneae,</hi> as the ſpiders web, wherin the leſſer flies are caught, but the greater breake thorow: yet <hi>Gods Law</hi> is a <hi>Net,</hi> which catcheth all <hi>alike:</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>Rete Vulcanium,</hi> like Vulcans iron net, binding <hi>Princes with chaines, and Nobles with linkes of iron:</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 149.8.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.</p>
            <p>No diſtinction of <hi>ſexe;</hi> but <hi>male, aſwell as female:</hi> nor of <hi>nation,</hi> but <hi>Iew, aſwell as Gentile:</hi> nor of <hi>degree,</hi> but <hi>Prince, aſwell as people:</hi> nor of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16132:18"/>
               <hi>condition,</hi> but <hi>bond, aſwell as free:</hi> nor of <hi>age,</hi> but <hi>old, aſwell as yong. All</hi> are fiſh for this this net, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all are <hi>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What though they be but <hi>aequiuocall men?</hi> men in <hi>name</hi> only, not in <hi>nature?</hi> what though <hi>beaſts</hi> in the ſhape of men, ſuch as <hi>S. Paul</hi> fought with at <hi>Epheſus,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.32.</note> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. Nay, what though <hi>Diuels incarnate,</hi> in the likeneſſe of men, ſuch as were <hi>Peter</hi> that denied, and <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> that betraied his Maſter? Theſe muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be fiſht for; that of <hi>aequiuocall men,</hi> of <hi>beaſts,</hi> of <hi>Diuels,</hi> they may become <hi>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Euery <hi>yeſterdaies Sophiſter</hi> can tell you, that A <hi>man</hi> is <hi>Animal rationale, mortale, bipes;</hi> A reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, a mortall, a two-footed creature. Yet ſome forget that they are <hi>Reaſonable:</hi> Others that they are <hi>Mortall:</hi> Others, that they are <hi>two-footed.</hi> Al theſe muſt be fiſht for, that they may become <hi>Men.</hi> They that forget them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be <hi>Reaſonable,</hi> are <hi>voluptuous</hi> and <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall men,</hi> led only by the <hi>ſenſuall</hi> part of the ſoule, which is common to vs with beaſts: not by <hi>reaſon,</hi> which doth diſtinguiſh vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beaſts. Theſe muſt bee fiſht for, that their
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16132:18"/>
               <hi>reaſon</hi> may be rectified.</p>
            <p>They that forget themſelues to bee <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall,</hi> are <hi>coutous men,</hi> who (if<note n="ſ" place="margin">Hieronym.</note> 
               <hi>S. Hieromes</hi> rule be true, that <hi>Facilè contemnit omnia, qui ſe ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per cogitat moriturum:</hi> He wil eaſily be brought to contemne all mortall things, who will but conſider his owne mortality) do heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by manifeſt vnto the world, that they think not themſelues mortall, becauſe they will part with nothing; Nay, as if they were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready immortall, they will not allow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues meat for the mainteina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall life. Theſe muſt alſo bee fiſht for, that their <hi>thoughts</hi> may be mortified.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, they that forget themſelues to be <hi>two-footed,</hi> are ſuch <hi>as care neither for God, nor man.</hi> They haue not <hi>one</hi> foot of their affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction carrying them towards God, <hi>another</hi> towards their neighbour: but they are <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drupedes,</hi> foure-footed, as <hi>horſe and mule:</hi> and <hi>Multipedes,</hi> many-footed, as <hi>flies and ſpiders;</hi> that is, as<note n="t" place="margin">Eccl. 9.3.</note> the <hi>Son of Sirac</hi> termes the harlot, <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>Multiuoli,</hi> of many wils and affections, yet neuer a good. Theſe muſt alſo be fiſht
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16132:19"/>for, that their <hi>affections</hi> may bee qualified.</p>
            <p>Theſe, &amp; the like to theſe, are <hi>the fiſh</hi> that wee muſt fiſh for: and how well wee haue fiſht for them, we muſt one day giue an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. For at that great and generall <hi>market-day</hi> of foules (the day of iudgement) then ſhall the Lord ſay to thoſe that are <hi>preachers,</hi> as he ſaid to thoſe <hi>fiſhers,</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Ioan. 21.22.</note> 
               <hi>Io.</hi> 21. <hi>Venite nunc, &amp; prandete,</hi> Come, and dine. And when they ſhall anſwer, <hi>Wherwith Lord?</hi> Then ſhall he ſay vnto them as vnto thoſe fiſhers; <hi>Afferte de piſcibus, quos prendidiſtis:</hi> Bring hither of the fiſhes that ye haue caught. O Lord! What ſhall then become of ſuch a Preacher as ſhall be faine to ſay; Lord, I neuer fiſht for <hi>ſoules?</hi> My fiſhing hath beene onely for <hi>great place,</hi> for preferment, for money, for fame, for friendſhip, and the like: But as for men I nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caught, nor fiſht for any.</p>
            <p n="6">6, And laſtly, <hi>Quoad Praemium.</hi> In regard of the <hi>remuneration or reward</hi> of their office. Which <hi>office,</hi> as in my text <hi>it ſelfe</hi> may ſeeme to be <hi>a reward</hi> of a precedent worke, becauſe our Sauiour promiſeth, if they will follow
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16132:19"/>him, of <hi>fiſhermen,</hi> to make them <hi>fiſhers of men,</hi> (and needs muſt that be a labour worth the labour, which is promiſed as a reward of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour) ſo to ſhew, that they haue more than their labour for their paines, the Scripture tells vs, that they that conuert many vnto righteouſneſſe, <hi>Fulgebunt quaſiſtellae,</hi> ſhal ſhine as the ſtarres for euer and euer,<note n="*" place="margin">Dan. 12.3</note> 
               <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>And the twelue <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſhall ſit vpon the 12 <hi>thrones,</hi> and iudge the 12 <hi>tribes</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Matth. 19.28.</note> 
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. <hi>Num ſedebunt?</hi> What? ſhall they ſit indeed (ſaith<note n="y" place="margin">Theophyl. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Theophylact</hi>) No: but by their <hi>ſitting</hi> is ſignified the <hi>excellency</hi> of their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. <hi>Non enim creaturae eſt ſedere, ſed ſanctae Trinitatis: creaturae autem tanquam ancillae eſt ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re:</hi> For it is not for the creature to ſit, but for the holy Trinity. As for the creature, it well beſeemeth it to ſtand like a ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dmaid, ſaith the ſame<note n="z" place="margin">Theophyl. in Luc. <hi>22.30.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Theophylact in Luc.</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>And againe, when it is ſaid in the ſame place, that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſhall <hi>eat,</hi> and <hi>drinke</hi> with Chriſt in his kingdome; What? (ſaith hee) ſhall they eat and drinke with him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed? No, this is but a metaphor borrowed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16132:20"/>from thoſe that are wont to be graced and honoured by Princes. <hi>Nam qui cum regibus coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, videntur primos honores ſortiri:</hi> For, to be admitted to ſup with a King, why its the greateſt honour that can bee done a man. So that, this is it that Chriſt would ſignifie, when he ſaith that his Apoſtles ſhall <hi>ſit, and eat, and drinke with him</hi> in his kingdom, that he values &amp; prefers them before all the world beſides.</p>
            <p>What then? Is this all the reward of Gods Miniſters? (though, if it were, they had cauſe enough whereof to reioice) But haue they onely a <hi>plentifull reward in heauen,</hi> and is their reward none at all heere on earth? What? Muſt they ſerue at the Altar, and yet not liue by the Altar? Muſt they neither haue <hi>Partem quotam,</hi> a tenth part, nor yet <hi>Aliquotam,</hi> any part at all of the increaſe of their flocke?</p>
            <p>Such indeed (for the moſt part) is our now-adaies religion. The mainteinance of the Miniſter is held but a matter arbitrary, and the paiment of tithes only a ceremonie determined and ended together with the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16132:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>ceremoniall Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> But the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture whereby they are due (witneſſe the tithes that <hi>Abraham</hi> before the Law paid <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> the <hi>Prieſt</hi> of the moſt high God,<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 14.18.</note> 
               <hi>Ge.</hi> 14.) though it ran along with the ceremoniall Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> yet was it not determinable with that Law, no more than was the <hi>Decalogue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet a monſter it is to ſee, how <hi>the ſheep</hi>) ſhall I ſay, or <hi>goats?</hi>) rebell againſt their <hi>ſhepheard:</hi> as if he that feedes the flocke were not worthy to be fed with the milke of the flocke: and fleece hee ſhal haue none, but that prouerbial wool, <hi>Lanam Caprinam,</hi> goats wooll: that is (by their good will) none at all.</p>
            <q>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Martial. l. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Et piſcatorem piſcis amare potes?</hi>
            </q>
            <p>It greeues the fiſh, that the fiſherman (be he neuer ſo painfull) ſhould make a poore liuing by them. Doubtleſſe, this was neuer Gods mind. He would not that his Prieſts ſhould want in the Law: much leſſe in the Goſpell.<note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 28.</note> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 28. <hi>The Prieſts hand muſt be filled:</hi> He muſt not be in want; nor muſt <hi>the mouth of the oxe, that treadeth out the corne be muzled:</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Deut. 25.4</note> 
               <hi>Deut.</hi> 25. And perhaps it was not without myſtery, that our Sauiour Chriſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16132:21"/>cauſed a <hi>fiſh to pay tribute</hi> for him, and <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Matt. 17.27.</note> 17. but that thereby hee would teach <hi>Spirituall fiſh,</hi> to giue tribute to whom tribute, honour to whom honour, tithe to whom tithe belongeth.</p>
            <p>Had not <hi>S. Paul</hi> peremptorily and flatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, that the mainteinance of Gods Miniſter muſt not be a minced and curtall mainteinance, but large and liberal, he would neuer haue char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him with hoſpitality:<note n="f" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.2.</note> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. A duty which the people are as ready to exact, as <hi>S. Paul</hi> to enioine: and yet they will not allow him wherewithall. Which how much better is it than <hi>Phataohs</hi> tyranny,<note n="g" place="margin">Exod. 5.8</note> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 5. who required of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> their full tale of bricke, and yet he would not allow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtraw wherwith to make it?</p>
            <p>Thus as the <hi>aſcent</hi> to <hi>Salomons</hi> throne was <hi>Per ſex gradus,</hi> by ſix degrees or ſteps,<note n="h" place="margin">1. Reg. 10.19.</note> 1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 10. ſo by <hi>ſix degrees or ſteps</hi> (as ye haue heard) doth the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter riſe to his <hi>throne of dignity.</hi> All which, as on the one ſide, they ſhould reare and eleuate the thoughts of the miniſter from the center to the ſphaere, and remember him to walke worthy ſo worthy a calling; becauſe (as<note n="i" place="margin">Hieronym.</note> 
               <hi>S. Hierome</hi> pithily ſpeakes) <hi>Malus Sacerdos de Sacerdotioſuo crimen ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirit,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16132:21"/>non dignitatem:</hi> If the Miniſter be lewd, his miniſtery doth not grace, but blemiſh him. And as<note n="k" place="margin">Lucian in Piſcator.</note> 
               <hi>Lucian</hi> notes of <hi>ſtage-plaiers,</hi> that if they miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act but a ſeruant, or meſſenger onely, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: it is but a ſmall ſlip; but if they act <hi>Iupiter</hi> or <hi>Hercules</hi> vnworthily, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: it is a foule and inexpiable fault: So if the Miniſter did miſact but an earthly Prince only, his fault were more tolerable: but foraſmuch as hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents the king of heauen and earth, it can be no leſſe than damnable;</p>
            <p>So ſhould they likewiſe on the other ſide, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the people, to haue the Miniſter in <hi>ſingular reuerence</hi> for his work ſake; and if for none other cauſe, yet therefore to honour him becauſe hee is <hi>Gods Aſſe;</hi> as the Iewes ſpred their garments in the way, content that the <hi>Aſſe</hi> ſhould <hi>tread</hi> vpon them becauſe he carried Chriſt,<note n="l" place="margin">Matt. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Matt.</hi> 21. And though the Miniſter be vnworthy ſo great an honour (for <hi>who is ſufficient for theſe things,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16.</note> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.) yet <hi>ſo to eſteeme of him, as of the Miniſter of Chriſt, and diſpoſer of the ſecrets of God:</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16.</note> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. For why ſhould <hi>piety</hi> denie that to <hi>Gods Miniſter,</hi> which <hi>policy</hi> will affoord a mortall <hi>Princes officer,</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:16132:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>whom albeit his after-carriage may declare to bee vnworthy the honour whereunto his <hi>Liege</hi> hath aduanced him, yet will the people ſay with him in<note n="o" place="margin">Tacitus.</note> 
               <hi>Tacitus; Tuorum conſiliorum ſocium, tua officia in republicâ capeſsentem colebamus:</hi> Becauſe he is thy counſellour, and thine officer (ô King) we ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him.</p>
            <p>Howbeit ſuch is the iniquitie of theſe times, that as the <hi>ſhadow</hi> went backward <hi>ten degrees,</hi> in the <hi>Dial of Ahaz,</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">2. Reg. 10 11.</note> 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 20. So ten degrees, and more do the <hi>ſhadows of Chriſt</hi> (the <hi>miniſters of Chriſt</hi>) go backward in the account and eſtimate of the world, ſooner than ſtep forward; I ſay not <hi>ſix degrees,</hi> but <hi>one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For whereas none is thought <hi>too-good,</hi> to be a <hi>Princes Embaſſadour;</hi> they thinke none <hi>too-bad</hi> to be the <hi>Embaſſadour of God the Prince of Princes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Were<note n="q" place="margin">Plutarch. in Cat. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior.</note> 
               <hi>Cato Maior</hi> now aliue againe, to ſee the halt, and the blinde marked out to this beſt and greateſt ſeruice, might he not worthilie ſcoffe at them, as ſometimes he did at the <hi>Roman</hi> Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours, one wounded in the head, and another in the foot? <hi>Mittit Populus Romanus legationem, quae nec caput, nec pedes habet:</hi> Gods Embaſſage is like a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16132:22"/>
               <hi>ſickmans dreame,</hi> that hath neither <hi>head,</hi> nor <hi>foot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heeretofore Elder-brothers were Prieſts by birth-right: but now the Prieſthood is the birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right of yonger brothers. Yonger brothers are made Prieſts, and Prieſts made yonger brothers.</p>
            <p>Heeretofore <hi>Kings</hi> themſelues diſdained not to be <hi>Prieſts:</hi> and hereafter <hi>Kings and Prieſts</hi> muſt once againe be attoned,<note n="r" place="margin">Apoc. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1. And yet now (forſooth) euery petite Gentleman of the firſt head, thinks himſelfe all-too-good for ſo meane an office. Its grace enough to the Miniſtery, if hee but vouchſafe to turne one of: his ſeruing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men out of his into Gods ſeruice: out of his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery into a Church-liuing.</p>
            <p>Theſe, &amp; the like diſgraces, did they but wound our owne perſons, we could the better ſwallow them: But <hi>Cùm per latera noſtra petitur Eccleſia, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitur Chriſtus,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thorow our ſides the Church of Chriſt, yea Chriſt himſelfe is goared, then to be ſilent, it were <hi>Languor, non patientia;</hi> ſtupidity, rather than patience. Then high time (if yet time enough) to ſpeake.</p>
            <p>Heere can I hardly containe my ſelfe, but that, like another <hi>Peter,</hi> I ſhould draw the <hi>blade of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16132:23"/>Gods word,</hi> and draw <hi>blood</hi> at <hi>Malchus</hi> his eare in the quarrell of my Lord and Maſter Chriſt. But the time hath already ouer-maſtered mee; and ſhould I draw, it would bid mee <hi>ſheath vp my ſword againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet this I ſay (for a <hi>parting-blow</hi>) to the <hi>prophane and Atheiſticall deriders,</hi> of theſe daies, that take pleaſure in belching out diſgraces againſt the Miniſter, making him no better than the <hi>very paring,</hi> and <hi>filth,</hi> and <hi>purgament,</hi> and <hi>off-ſcouring of all things;</hi> that<note n="ſ" place="margin">Philelf. ep. l. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>In expuentis recidit barbam, quod in coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum expuitur:</hi> The diſgrace rebounds backe vpon their owne pates: they doe but foame out their owne ſhame: they bewray aſmuch malice as little religion.</p>
            <p>For if, <hi>Feare the Lord, and honour his Prieſts</hi> muſt goe together, as<note n="t" place="margin">Sirac. 7.31.</note> 
               <hi>Sirac</hi> 7. then it ſeemes, that whoſo honoreth not his Prieſts, feareth not the Lord. And if, <hi>Quench not the ſpirit; Deſpiſe not propheſie,</hi> muſt go hand in hand, as<note n="u" place="margin">Theſſ. 5.20.</note> 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. then the inference muſt be, that whoſo deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth propheſie, quencheth the ſpirit. And if (as our Sauiour tels his Diſciples,<note n="*" place="margin">Luc. 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>Luc.</hi> 10. <hi>Hee that heareth you, heareth mee:</hi> and, <hi>Hee that deſpiſeth
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16132:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>you, despiſeth mee;</hi> then, as truly as God is a iealous God,<note n="x" place="margin">Exod. 20.5.</note> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. (as iealous of his owne honor, as euer huſband of his own wife) he wil not leaue the deſpights and indignities done to his Miniſters vnreuenged.</p>
            <p>And (for concluſion) I will ad this corollary of comfort to my brethren <hi>fellow-fiſhermen, &amp; fellow laborers</hi> in this holy &amp; heauenly function; that as <hi>Aulico paru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> refert quomodo a caeteris aeſtimetur, dummodò principi ſe probet:</hi> Little cares the Courtier how o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers eſteeme of him, ſo that he approoue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to his Prince, who is able to exalt and bring him to honour: ſo they need not much reſpect how little men reſpect them (eclipſing, extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating, maligning their calling) ſo that they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue themſelues vnto God, who both can, and will heereafter highly aduance them.</p>
            <p>That bright, glorious, and capacious globe of the Sun, is (to ſee to) but <hi>Inſtar pilae pedalis,</hi> No bigger than a foot-ball: Yet is it no leſſe than <hi>Luxmundi,</hi> The light of the world: So they, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit in the eies of men they are no better than a foot-ball, a very play-game fit to be kickt and ſpurnd at; yet are they in Gods eies (who ſeeth
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16132:24"/>not as man ſeeth) <hi>Luxmundi,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Matt. 5.14.</note> 
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. glorious and beautifull as is the Sun in the firmament, farre aboue which they ſhall one day be exalted in the higheſt heauens; there for euer to ſhine in glory with him who is <hi>Sol Iuſtitiae,</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Malac. 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>Mal.</hi> 4. euen the <hi>true ſonne of righteouſneſſe Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
